{"tossups": [{"question": "A conservative newspaper in this city was run for years by Colonel Robert McCormick, whose slogan\u201cWorld\u2019s Greatest Newspaper\u201d was applied to the local radio station, WGN. A paper from this city published the erroneous headline \u201cDewey Defeats Truman\u201d during the election of 1948. According to legend, Mrs. O\u2019Leary\u2019s cow knocking over a lantern caused a Great Fire in October 1871 in this city. For ten points, name this home of the<em> Tribune</em>, the largest city in Illinois.", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man suggested that his superior, Sir Thomas Fairfax, give up his strong position to encourage a hasty attack by Prince Rupert at the Battle of Naseby. In 1653, this Roundhead dismissed the Rump Parliament, the small group of MPs who remained after Pride\u2019s Purge in 1648. Charles I was beheaded on orders of, for ten points, what leader of the New Model Army, known as \u201cOld Ironsides,\u201d who served as Lord Protector after the English Civil War?", "answer": "Oliver<b> Cromwell</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Apartment buildings in this city were called<em> insulae</em>, and it contained a sewage system known as the Cloaca Maxima that drained into the Tiber River. This city was built on the Palatine, Capitoline, and five other hills. For ten points, name this ancient city whose entertainment venues included the Circus Maximus and the Colosseum, the capital of a vast Italian empire.", "answer": "ancient<b> Rome</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This city was sacked two years after the surrender of Alamut fortress by the Assassins. This city was ruled by al-Musta\u2019sim, until he was legendarily killed by being wrapped in a rug and trampled by horses, thereby preventing the shedding of royal blood. In 1258, Hulagu Khan made the Tigris River \u201crun black with ink\u201d after his Mongols sacked, for ten points, what capital of the Abbasid Empire that now serves as the capital of modern Iraq?", "answer": "<b> Baghdad</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s Pioneer Park, on top of Telegraph Hill, contains a tower built in memory of Lillie Hitchcock Coit. Its Russian Hill neighborhood is known for a one-block stretch of Lombard Street with eight hairpin turns. This city\u2019s Castro neighborhood was the launching pad for the political career of Harvey Milk. The Haight-Ashbury district nurtured the \u201chippie\u201d counterculture in, for ten points, what \u201ccity by the bay\u201din Northern California?", "answer": "<b> San Francisco</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s criticism of the Vietnam War led Lyndon Johnson to accuse him of playing \u201ctoo much football without a helmet.\u201d Though this man signed the Helsinki Accords, he asserted that \u201cthere is no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe\u201d during a debate with Jimmy Carter, hampering his re-election bid. For ten points, name this president who succeeded, and controversially pardoned, Richard Nixon.", "answer": "Gerald Rudolph<b> Ford</b> (or Leslie Lynch<b> King</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This virus\u2019<em> env</em> gene codes for the gp120 envelope glycoprotein. A disease caused by this virus was briefly, misleadingly called GRID. Using a molecular clock, scientists were able to trace back the origins of this virus to early twentieth century West Africa. This retrovirus infects and lowers the count of helper T cells. Infection by this virus took the lives of Freddie Mercury, Michel Foucault, and Rock Hudson during an explosive epidemic in the 1980s. For ten points, name this virus that causes AIDS.", "answer": "<b> HIV</b> (or<b> human immunodeficiency virus</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "Another of this country\u2019s planes disappeared over the South China Sea in the same year.", "answer": "<b> Malaysia</b> (accept word forms; accept<b> Malaysia</b>(n) Airlines)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "As a bimetallist, William Jennings Bryan supported the \u201cfreeing\u201d of this resource in his \u201cCross of Gold\u201dspeech. For ten points, name this precious metal.", "answer": "<b> silver</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Massive protests in this country began after a speech in Qom during the 15 Khordad Movement. A series of land reforms and pro-Western measures led to further unrest, culminating in a massacre at Jaleh Square on Black Friday. The SAVAK secret police terrorized this nation and executed opponents of its ruler, Mohammed Reza Shah Pahlavi. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern country where a 1979 Islamic revolution was led by Ayatollah Khomeini and flooded the streets of Tehran.", "answer": "Islamic Republic of<b> Iran</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, the Little Willie prototype led to the development of male and female vehicles first used at the Battle of Flers-Courcelette. A plane called the \u201cScourge\u201d was built during this war after the development of the interrupter. Other vehicles introduced during this war included the Sopwith Camel and the Fokker Dr.I, [d r 1] which was flown by the Red Baron. Tanks and airplanes revolutionized warfare in, for ten points, what early 20th century war, whose trench warfare was called to armistice in 1918?", "answer": "<b> World War I</b> (or the<b> Great War</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s superiors forced him to agree to the Convention of Cintra; he was later court-martialed for it after his enemy escaped. This man\u2019s victories at Salamanca and Vitoria were key in winning the Peninsular War and defending his ally, Portugal. This general fought Marshal Ney to a standstill at the Battle of Quatre-Bras two days before his troops, alongside Gebhard von Blucher, ended the Hundred Days campaign. For ten points, name this British general who won the Battle of Waterloo.", "answer": "Arthur<b> Wellesley</b>, 1st Duke of<b> Wellington</b> (accept either)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "James Blaine and Robert Todd Lincoln were witnesses to this event, which took place in the Baltimore and Potomac Railroad Station. The perpetrator of this crime chose a revolver for its ivory handle, which would look good in a museum. The victim of this event survived for over two months, despite the summer heat and incompetent doctors, before he died and was succeeded by a Stalwart. For ten points, name this 1881 crime, committed by Charles Guiteau [ghee-toe], which elevated Chester Arthur to the presidency.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> of James<b> Garfield</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The diplomats that negotiated this treaty included Lords Sumner and Cunliffe, the\u201cHeavenly Twins.\u201d This treaty included global recognition of the International Opium Convention and the establishment of the Free City of (+) Danzig. The issue of Vietnamese indepenence was ignored during its negotiations, despite the pleas of then-student Ho Chi Minh. Article 231 of this treaty, known as the War (*)</b> Guilt clause, required harsh reparations that were accurately predicted to lead to another war. For ten points, name this treaty, signed in France in 1919, that ended World War I.", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Versailles</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The 2010 U.S. Olympic hockey team wore dog tags honoring this action done by Brendan Burke. The Nets\u2019 number 98 jersey became a top-seller after its wearer performed this action, and another man did it after leaving Leeds United for the (+) L.A. Galaxy in May 2013. A former SEC Defensive Player of the Year for the University of Missouri dropped to the seventh round of the 2014 (*)</b> NFL draft after performing this action. For ten points, name this action performed by Jason Collins, Robbie Rogers, and Michael Sam when they publicized their sexuality.", "answer": "<b> coming out</b> (accept equivalents like<b> telling</b> people that they are<b> gay</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man, who defined his philosophy in</b><em><b> The Story of My Experiments with Truth</b></em><b>, signed a pact with Lord Irwin before the Second Round Table Conference to discuss dominion status. This man called for the use of (+)</b><em><b> khadi</b></em><b>, or homespun cloth, in opposition to foreign textiles, and he traveled to Dandi to violate a foreign tax during the (*)</b> Salt March. This man advocated for a form of civil disobedience called<em> satyagraha</em>. For ten points, name this pacifist and leader of the Indian independence movement.", "answer": "<b> M</b>ahatma<b> Gandhi</b> (or<b> M</b>ohandas Karamchand<b> Gandhi</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>On this island, Venetian settlers built a still-standing series of fortifications in Famagusta.</b> <b>A political movement on this island known as</b><em><b> enosis</b></em><b> sought to (+)</b> <b>unite it with another</b> <b>country. In 1960, this island gained its independence from the UK, who still controls a military bases at Akrotiri here. A 1974 invasion of this island led to its partition along the (*)</b> Green Line. For ten points, name this Mediterranean island, divided into a Greek-speaking southern majority and a self-proclaimed \u201cTurkish Republic\u201d in the north.", "answer": "<b> Cyprus</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man focused on Owen Lattimore in the Tydings Committee hearings, after which his charges were deemed a \u201cfraud and a hoax.\u201d Early in his career, this man fought wartime</b> <b>price controls after receiving a $20,000 personal loan from (+)</b> <b>Pepsi, earning him the</b> <b>nickname the \u201cPepsi-Cola Kid.\u201d After he accused the Army of being soft, Joseph Welch asked this man \u201cHave (*)</b> you no sense of decency?\u201d in Congressional hearings. For ten points, name this Wisconsin senator who claimed there were 205 communists in the State Department during the Red Scare.", "answer": "Joseph<b> McCarthy</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man issued the Decree on Peace, which called for no indemnities or annexations, and passed land reform with the Decree on Land. This man condemned the government</b> <b>in his (+)</b> <b>April Theses and began a series of economic reforms called the New Economic</b> <b>April Theses and began a series of economic reforms called the New Economic</b> <b>Policy. Alexander Kerensky\u2019s government was overthrown in the (*)</b> <b>Policy. Alexander Kerensky\u2019s government was overthrown in the (*)</b> October Revolution by this man\u2019s forces, who defeated the White Army in the resulting civil war. For ten points, name this leader of the Bolsheviks and founder of the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Vladimir Ilyich<b> Lenin</b> (or Vladimir Ilyich<b> Ulyanov</b>) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s troops refused to cross the Beas [bay-ahs] River, after which this man</b> <b>built twelve giant altars and ended his final campaign. This man forced his generals</b> <b>to have a mass wedding at (+)</b> <b>Susa. This man\u2019s army used the extra-long sarissa</b> <b>pike and had an elite cavalry corps called the Companions. He fought at the Battle of</b> <b>Chaeronea alongside his father, Philip II, to subdue the Greek cities, and he inflicted</b> <b>a series of defeats at (*) </b> Issus and Gaugamela on his rival, Darius III. For ten points, name this Macedonian conqueror of the Persian Empire.", "answer": "<b> Alexander the Great</b> (or<b> Alexander III</b> of Macedon)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}